we live on a terrifying Planet but not
all life sees it that way cuz for every
extreme environment that exists there's
an extremophile that thrives within it
today I'm going to explain every type of
extremophile to you from least extreme
to most extreme but we need to start by
defining extremophile an extremophile is
an organism that lives optimally under
extreme conditions what makes conditions
extreme well it's kind of subjective
there's no official rule but it usually
just describes an environment that the
vast majority of Life Would Die horrible
deaths within additionally to be an
extremophile it's not enough to survive
but to thrive in the extreme If an
organism can survive an extreme
condition but can't grow or reproduce in
it it would be considered extremo
tolerant not extremophilic okay that's
all you need to know let's start off hot
with thermophiles organisms that thrive
in high temperatures anywhere from 41°
all the way to
122° C this is the grand prismatic
spring the largest hot spring in the
United States it has this unique rainbow
coloration hence its name created by
thermophilic microbes living around the
edges of the hot water these colors are
created by pigments called keratinoid
which are red orange or yellow and by
chlorophyll the same stuff that gives
plants their green color the blue in the
center of the spring is just the color
of the water because the center is
actually so hot that it's completely
sterile so none of the local microbes
can survive in there when our body
temperatures go even a single degree or
two above Baseline our proteins begin to
denature within us suffice it to say
most cells are very temperature
sensitive and are unable to survive high
temperatures especially not to the level
of Hot Springs deep sea hydrothermal
vents and ferals so for thermophiles to
live they need to have thermostable
enzymes proteins and D DNA that don't
get completely destroyed by boiling
temperatures and while plenty of them
have adapted these traits others have
found their own solution sulfolobus is a
genus of thermophilic archa that has
their DNA constantly damaged due to the
high temperatures of their environment
to deal with this they aggregate with
each other and exchange genetic material
to repair damaged DNA through homologous
recombination a process you may be
familiar with if you've taken a genetics
course this DNA exchange solves the
denaturation issue without needing to
develop extreme heat resistance because
instead of trying to prevent DNA
destruction cobus just constantly
regenerates its DNA with the help of
neighboring cells there's evidence that
these thermophilic bacteria are among
the earliest bacteria ever so some think
that their ability to exchange DNA may
be a primitive trait that would go on to
evolve into sexual behavior in another
lineage on the other side of the pillow
we have psychrophiles which thrive in
cold temperatures all the way down to
-20° C life is mostly made of water and
since water freezes at 0° negative
temperatures don't exactly make the most
sense to survive it now mammals have
solved this by being warm-blooded and
regulating our internal temperature to
still be warm even in the cold but this
is a temporary fix we can't stay in the
cold permanently like psychrophiles have
to at least not without ways to heat
ourselves up in the process in
1897 the Belgian Antarctic expedition
was launched the first ever expedition
to spend a winter in Antarctica here
they discovered the largest purely
terrestrial animal native to the
continent the Antarctic mij a flightless
fly that was able to survive year round
in Antarctica even being able to
withstand being frozen they do this by
having tons of hydrogen bonds to
stabilize proteins and keep membranes
from stiffening too much as well as heat
shock and anti-freeze proteins to help
with tolerating extreme temperatures
there are actually several insects that
do well in the freezing cold some of
them live in the cold permanently but
others only do it for the winter season
preparing themselves in a process called
cold hardening this is the same thing
that many plants do before winter here
in Canada the trees shed their leaves
every fall relocating their nutrient
stores from their leaves into
underground storage organs so that they
can better survive the prolonged period
of cold but this hardly compares to
cyrilic bacteria that can enter the
viable but non-culturable state or vbnc
this state allows bacteria to be
completely frozen in ice unable to do
anything yet survive for what seems like
forever some bacteria cells have
survived over 500,000 years in the
permafrost of Antarctica Canada and
Siberia and have even been revived upon
leaving the ice it's because of this
that a lot of people are afraid of an
ancient superbug a deadly pathogen from
millions of years ago Frozen away under
layers of ice that we've had no time to
develop resistances for as the planet's
temperature continues to rise and the
ice continues to melt maybe it'll come
back alive and infect us and then we're
screwed this probably won't happen but
it's definitely not impossible so I see
why people are worried hopefully we'll
be fine hopefully acidophiles are able
to thrive in very acidic environments
usually ph5 or lower but the most
acidophilic organism microbes in the
genus picris are able to grow at pH
levels of negative
0.06 the reason acid irritates our skin
or Burns entirely through is because
they're proton donors this means that
they provide hydrogen ions to a lot of
molecular compounds which can completely
restructure it and ruin its intended
functioning proteins sugars cell walls
and DNA can all be irreversibly damaged
from exposure to strong acids so most
acidophiles use proton pumps to rapidly
push out hydrogen ions from their
cytoplasm and maintain a neutral pH but
there are exceptions to this the
bacteria acetobacter acti has an
acidified cytoplasm meaning that all the
proteins in its genome have evolved acid
stability as a side effect to this a ATI
can react with ethanol and produce
acetic acid the primary component of
vinegar so it's actually used for a lot
of industrial Productions acidophiles
may turn out to be more useful than
previously thought especially because
human pollution is causing a lot of
environments to have higher pH levels
maybe will need to genetically engineer
the perfect acidophile in order to
neutralize this the opposite of an
acidophile is an alkaliphile where
optimal growth occurs in basic
conditions ph9 or above sodal Lakes are
bodies of water that have high
alkalinity usually between pH 9 and 12
due to their high concentrations of
sodium bicarbonate despite these
seemingly inhospitable circumstances
soda Lakes are actually the most
productive aquatic environments on Earth
they have a rich divers of microbes
doing a lot of photosynthesis up to 16
times the global average of freshwater
lakes this leads to large algal blooms
creating all sorts of colorations on the
lake surface bases do the opposite of
acids in that they're proton acceptors
which can still mess up everything in
your body at the molecular level just by
taking a different path to get there
it's no coincidence that lie a base used
to make soap is also used for disposing
corpses as it can break down every part
of the human body all the way down to
the bone among extremophiles many
organisms qualify for more than one
extremophilic category this makes sense
cuz naturally extreme conditions tend to
be extreme in more ways than one the
deep ocean is extremely cold has really
high pressure and low nutritional
availability hydrothermal vents have
high temperatures high pressures and
high acidities so to live in these
places you need to be a poly
extremophile we know of many poly
extremophiles but most research has
focused on resistances to individual
extremes so the considerations of how
multiple extremes affect an organism and
its ecology and evolution is barely
understood but I figured this would be
the perfect place to introduce
everyone's favorite the main character
of extremophiles the tardigrade
tardigrades or water bears are famous
for being able to withstand pretty much
anything extreme temperatures pressure
radiation starvation and even the vacuum
of space in 2021 a tardigrade was cooled
to 10 millin just barely above absolute
zero and after 420 hours it came back to
life Believe It or Not tardigrades being
extremophiles is actually a
misconception they do require a more
moderate environment to reproduce so
they're actually extrema tolerance not
extremophiles though of course most
people don't know that distinction so
they refer to them as extremophiles
anyways which is fine but I think it's
most accurate to call them hyper poly
extremo tolerance and I will get back to
them in a second moving on we have piles
which optimally grow in environments
with high hydrostatic pressures up to 10
megapascals all piles are poly
extremophiles because High pressures
tend to be found in places that are
really hot or really cold an example of
a thermophilic pizza file is the archa
pyrococcus which can be found in deep
sea hydrothermal vents and an example of
a psychrophilic pesophile is kellia
Marin Mania which was discovered from
the body of a decaying amphipod at the
bottom of the Marana trench in case you
don't know the Mariana Trench is the
deepest Oceanic trench on Earth for
reference the theoretical limit of a
diver is 1,000 M deep and a 100
atmospheres of pressure any more would
completely crush your body the bottom of
the Mariana Trench Challenger Valley is
10,816 M deep and Exhibits a pressure of
1,071 atmospheres there's a reason why
deep sea equipment needs to be carefully
constructed to survive the pressures of
deep Waters we wouldn't want to end up
on a submersible looking for the Titanic
which was poorly made to withstand deep
sea pressures causing everybody aboard
to die would we but that just goes to
show how insane sea Marin Mania is as
the most pesophilia
Valley capnophiles thrive in high
concentrations of carbon dioxide we
breathe in oxygen then breathe out CO2
plants and other things take in CO2 for
photosynthesis creating energy and
oxygen but too much CO2 even for the
organisms that consume it is still going
to be toxic there's a capnophile that
infects our mouths called uh a greti Bor
acoy
commants I'm just going to call it Greg
Greg causes periodontitis or gum disease
which I probably contracted from trying
to pronounce its full government name
because we constantly emit CO2 from our
mouths Greg has adapted to become a
capnophile and withstand the CO2
capnophiles aren't extensively studied
so I don't really have too much more to
say about them they aren't really used
for any practical reasons besides uh
Mania
Su suck suen producin which has
attracted some interest in the
production of succinic acid which is
used in food beauty products and
medicine but yeah that's really the
extent of capnophiles I guess you could
use their names in the world's hardest
spelling be as well you know I get a lot
of comments along the lines of I don't
really learn anything in school but I do
when I watch your videos it turns out
learning is more engaging when you enjoy
it and you seek it out yourself and
that's exactly what you can do with
brilliant who is kindly sponsoring
today's video brilliant is where you
learn by doing with thousands of
interactive lessons in data science math
programming and AI whether you're
learning a new skill or or brushing up
on old ones brilliant provides an easyto
usee platform that is designed to be the
most effective way to learn their
interactive lessons made by an
award-winning team of teachers
researchers and professionals focus on
core principles to help you build
understanding from the ground up and
their approach to Hands-On problem
solving is proven to be six times more
effective than watching lecture videos
I'm actually currently using brilliant
to learn how to code I'm learning the
essential coding elements I'm using
python to create my first program and
I'm just over all learning to think more
like a developer it's always been a
dream of mine to make a game or an app
of some sort and Brilliant is helping me
achieve that all by spending a couple
minutes on my phone every morning to try
everything brilliant has to offer for 30
days free and get 20% off an annual
premium subscription visit brilliant.org
sdan inblue you can also scan the QR
code on screen or visit the link in the
description thank you to brilliant for
sponsoring this video sulfa files high
sulfur dangerous they adapt to it I feel
like you guys get the pattern deep in
the fassi caves of Italy if you touch
your hand to the wall or ceiling you may
find it completely covered in boogers
because much like stalactites the rocks
that hang from walls and ceilings
snottite is a sulop file that hangs in
the same way snottite also called
snootles are actually mats of bacteria
which when grouped together have the
consistency of nasal mucus hence the
name these bacteria synthesize energy
from volcanic sulfuric compounds and
create sulfuric acid also known as
battery acid as a byproduct this is why
some scientists believe that snottite
may play a larger role in shaping caves
than previously thought in Sulfur Rich
environments the sulfuric acid they
produce may have chipped away at rocks
for millions of years contributing to
vast cave formations okay next up we
have extrem atrops which actually aren't
extremophiles but I feel like they fit
the vibe so I'm including them anyway
extrem trops are organisms that can
consume material that's generally
considered non-consumable Plastics
Metals compound discs circuits
radioactive waste and other long-term
pollutants are all examples of this
typically organic material decomposes
because of things eating them fungi mold
maggots vultures and more but since
nothing eats the inorganic stuff like
plastic which we produce a lot of these
days we have oceans and landfills full
of them in 2010 a strain of fungi
pestalotiopsis microspora was isolated
from stems of plants in the Ecuadorian
rainforest it was discovered to be able
to break down polyurethane a type of
plastic and since it's been actively
studied in the lab so that we may create
a solution to clean up plastic on a
large scale perhaps extrem atrops are
the key to reversing the damage we've
done to our planet by eating their way
through our problems speaking of eating
salt and sugar while tasty in our dishes
can be very deadly in high amounts if
you stepped in a pool with extreme salt
concentrations you would shrivel up and
dehydrate as water flushes out of you
via osmosis if you step in a very sugary
pool the high osmotic pressure would
cause the same thing to happen to you
the water in your cells would flush
right out but this isn't a problem for
halophiles which love high salt
environments and osmophile which love
high sugar environments the North Ronald
SE sheep from orcy Scotland has no
access to fresh water at all instead
they drink salt water and eat seaweed as
their only source of food the amount of
salt intake these guys have would kill
any other species of sheep meaning
they've adapted impressive resistances
to survive with this high salt diet
other halophiles tend to be
microorganisms that live in bodies of
salty water like the Great Salt Lake the
Dead Sea or the subsurface oceans of
Europa Europa is one of the few places
in our solar system that we know has
liquid water buried beneath its icy
surface so it's had a lot of notoriety
throughout the years hoping that we
might find life there NASA actually
recently launched the Europa Clipper so
that we might get a closer look at the
Moon and it's really cool stuff it's
going to use Mars's gravity to
essentially slingshot its way there and
it will hopefully reach Europa by 2030
revolve around it 50 times and send back
information that it finds it's likely
that europa's Waters have a high
solinity so if we did find life there
they would most likely be halophiles but
while water is one of our best
indicators for potential life some life
on Earth just doesn't seem to care for
it xeraph files thrive in extremely dry
conditions with little to no water
activity at all the cactus is probably
the most notable example of this they
survive in deserts with very little
rainfall storing up water and using it
very very sparingly there are a lot of
xerophilic plants called zeroes here is
my zeroy uh which is dead because I over
watered it uh I was told to water this
infrequently so I took that as like once
a week my logic was that in stardew
Valley you water the plants every day so
I was like a week's probably a long time
for a plant right uh no apparently I'm
stupid and it should have been more like
once a month but at least we can learn
from this that ziles are not just able
to survive on low water uh but they
often need low amounts of water uh or
else you get this and we can also learn
that just because someone has a biology
degree doesn't mean that they can
provide basic care to probably the
easiest plant to take care of of all
time but hey I got this other zeroy now
that I'm watering once a month and uh I
think it looks healthier maybe it was
commonly thought that if you removed
moisture from foods you could prevent it
from spoiling because most bacteria and
fungi that cause food to spoil need
water to live and while this does help
preserve food substantially because
xerophile exist it doesn't work
indefinitely xerophilic bacteria can
enter a state called anhydrobiosis where
where they have very little metabolic
activity to offset how little water
they're taking in similar to the vbnc
state that psychrophilic bacteria can
enter in case you haven't noticed by now
bacteria is very good at surviving turns
out staying single celled was the way to
go the next extreme environment we need
to talk about is an especially harsh
Place actually it's less of an
environment and more of a platform it's
called YouTube and extremophiles called
creators rely on organisms called
viewers to help suain stain themselves
creators are often required to ask
viewers to like and leave a comment and
subscribe in order to survive the
extreme hazard known as the algorithm so
it would really help me out if you did
any of these things let's get back to it
okay we've reached the extreme extremes
now starting with oligotrophs which can
sustain themselves in nutritionally
limited environments everything needs a
source of energy whether that's prey to
catch grass to graze on or sunlight to
bathe in but igots need as little as
possible possible they live in Barren
environments like Oceanic sediments
caves ice deep soils and aquifers this
is the m a fully aquatic oligotrophic
salamander that lives in underwater
caves they were first seen after being
washed up in 1689 by heavy rains and the
locals believed them to be baby cave
dragons I mean what else would you think
in 1689 look at these things they're
fully blind and navigate themselves
using chemo reception sound waves and an
electro receptor organ in their heads
that we're still trying to figure out
honestly these guys are really cool I
could do a whole video about them but
the bottom line is they can survive
longterm starvation reducing activity
and Metabolism in times of need and even
reabsorbing their own tissues in severe
situations in a controlled experiment
scientists found that MMS can survive up
to 10 years without any food pretty
crazy for a non bacteria I must say in
the case of bacteria though 4 km beneath
the world lays l VTO the largest
subglacial lake in Antarctica fully
encased in ice isolated from the rest of
the world the lake is large enough to
have several separate micro environments
with different microorganisms like fungi
and lots of different bacteria with
pretty much zero access to food these
igot trops may be perfect for simulating
extraterrestrial life again a great
parallel for life that might be on
Europa it's actually so crazy that life
lives here that some scientists think
it's a mistake they argue that any
microorganisms found in lake foso were
actually brought in by human researchers
accidentally contaminating the lake it's
sort of a mini conspiracy that I still
think is unresolved I personally want to
believe that life did reside there
before we got there but I don't know
Metallo tolerants are able to survive in
high levels of dissolved heavy metals
metal of the heavy variety especially
tends to not mesh very well with life
unless you're watching this 100 years in
the future and robots are legally
classified as alive and they've
overthrown us and all that but for now
there are only a few organisms that can
survive and even take advantage of
dissolved Metals in their environment
the Alpine Penny Crest is a plant that
can grow in soils with high
concentrations of zinc and cadmium it
takes up Metals in its roots and stores
them in its leaves to protect from
insects as the metal makes the leaves
toxic to chew on the Alpine Penny Crest
is often mentioned in talks of phyto
remediation the process of using plants
to clean the air soil and and Waters
from harmful contaminants so it may be a
key tool in cleaning up heavy metal
pollution around the planet there are
also several Metallo tolerant
microorganisms like ferroplasma and
enfers but otherwise it's a pretty
uncommon trait there really isn't a
reason to adapt resistance to Metals
since heavy metals being so predominant
in an environment that it induces a
selective pressure is just not that
frequent and finally we have radio
resistance which can withstand high
levels of ionizing radiation like UV
gamma rays and x-rays if there weren't
many reasons for an organism on Earth to
develop a Metallo tolerance there isn't
a single reason to become radioresistant
the majority of radiation in our solar
system comes from solar winds which
Earth's magnetic field keeps us very
safe from meaning the only ionizing
radiation that an organism would
encounter is regular sunlight which I
guess can cause cancer over long-term
exposure but is also the reason that
life is here in the first place and
man-made sources like microwaves X-rays
and nuclear waste these sources of
electromagnetic radiation did not exist
until we got here which is very recent
in the grand scheme of things so
organisms really should not have evolved
any level of radio resistance and yet
after the troby disaster researchers
found that a surprising number of plants
and animals did fairly well for
themselves despite the high radiation
levels here are the lethal doses of
radiation for different organisms of
course micro organisms are extremely
good at this particularly dooc caucus
radio durans and thermococcus Gamma
tolerans which both significantly
outclass even tardigrades here one
possible explanation for this is that
radio resistance developed as a side
effect of thermo tolerance the type of
cellular damage caused by high
temperatures is very similar to that
caused by high radiation levels so D
radio durans which is a hyper
thermophile may be radio resistant
simply as a consequence of this that
that or it could just be coincidental
the way that these organisms are may
just happen to not be affected by
ionizing radiation just because a trait
exists doesn't mean it's always a
specific adaptation towards something
evolution is a messy process and a lot
of things arise by chance accident or as
an unintended package deal with other
adaptations this may be why the plants
and animals near Chernobyl did better
than we thought perhaps life on Earth
isn't extremely resilient because it
needs to be but simply because it is but
what if we go past Earth to the extreme
conditions of other planets or even the
cold dead vacuum of space with no oxygen
no magnetic field and no gravity can our
native life survive the answer is yes
sort of we're we're working on it
there's no proper term for organisms
that can survive outer space so I'm
going to call them AST tolerance to be
astr tolerant you need to be poly
extremo tolerant cuz you need radio
resistance psychro tolerance oligotrophy
and more much more meaning our best bet
as always are microorganisms our friends
the tardigrades are the obvious example
here they are the first known animal to
ever survive exposure to outer space
they were taken to low earth orbit for
10 days exposed to the hard vacuum of
space and solar radiation and when they
were brought back to Earth most of them
survived and some were even able to
produce viable Offspring since then
plenty of other organisms have been
tested in low earth orbit simulated
conditions or even directly in space
including bacteria archa fungi lyans
viruses and more one of the most notable
to me is crew coxide opsis A genus of
bacteria that's thought to be able to
live on Mars crew coxide opsis can
photosynthesize in Far red light so it's
actually a prime candidate not just for
surviving Mars but for terraforming it
clearly expanding life into the stars is
going to heavily rely on studying
extremophiles as will cleaning up the
pollution on Earth and who knows what
else maybe one day we can genetically
engineer humans to survive extreme
conditions too I mean poly extremophile
engineering is already something that's
being explored so why not go extreme
with the implications of all this it's
all really cool stuff so I hope you guys
found some value from this video and
consider watching another one if you
enjoyed it thanks for watching
right